מזל טוב. Mazal tov. Good ערב ערב פסח. erev erev Pesach. Today's
דף daf is מ"א. mem aleph. We will be starting momentarily the
new פרק perek after finishing what is the biggest פרק perek in
ש"ס. Shas. But
we resume at the bottom of מ' עמוד ב', mem amud bet,
the very last of the narrow lines. We're talking about doing מצוות
mitzvot and the weight of מצוות mitzvot and so on. So the
previous משנה mishnah had spoken about anybody who does one מצווה, mitzvah,
you know, has all this good stuff, and if you don't do
one מצווה, mitzvah, then it's all bad. And it actually occurred to
me by the way, I just wanted to mention this one thing
although it's from yesterday, that the גמרא Gemara sort of interpreted it
like, well, if you're exactly 50/50, then one מצווה mitzvah tips the
scale, which to us seems a very narrow reading of the משנה
mishnah because the משנה mishnah seems to be just giving you an
enormous amount of weight for any one מצווה mitzvah that you do.
But it occurred to me that the end the way the גמרא
Gemara framed it about how you're supposed to look at yourself, right?
If you're always looking at yourself as if you're 50/50, then it's
not like the משנה'ס mishnah's talking only about the case of somebody
who's 50/50. It's basically saying for every individual, every time you're about
to do a מצווה, mitzvah, if you look at yourself like you're
exactly half merit and half demerit, then any מצווה mitzvah you do
has enormous consequence, and any not מצווה mitzvah that you're not doing,
right, has enormous consequence. So in a way it's a very profound
way of reading the משנה mishnah if you assume that what it
means is you look at yourself like it's always exactly in the
balance. And then it speaks about the enormous weight that any one
מצווה mitzvah will do or not doing one מצווה mitzvah will do.
So that's in terms of the previous משנה. mishnah. The next משנה
mishnah spoke about anybody who is במקרא במשנה ובדרך ארץ bamikra bamishnah
ubederech eretz does not sin quickly. So there it's sort of moving
beyond מצווה mitzvah and speaks about other things seemingly other than מצווה:
mitzvah: מקרא, mikra, משנה, mishnah, and דרך ארץ. derech eretz. Where I
mentioned מקרא mikra and משנה mishnah might be a way of understanding
מקרא, mikra, you know, is תנ"ך, Tanakh, which speaks about God, a
way of relating to God, a religious type of an orientation. משנה
mishnah could be הלכה. halakhah. What's דרך ארץ? derech eretz? So one
way of understanding דרך ארץ derech eretz means like he has a
פרנסה. parnassah. You work in the real world, you understand what it
means to actually labor and produce and not just be in like
a little bubble of your own, you know, problem about people that
could just learning, רמב"ם Rambam talks about this a lot. If you're
just learning and not getting a פרנסה parnassah and being supported by
the ציבור, tzibbur, then what does that do in terms of that
sense about, you know, entitlement and the sense about not understanding the
value of work and of labor, etc. But the other way of
reading דרך ארץ, derech eretz, which the רמב"ם Rambam says actually here
in פירוש המשניות, Perush HaMishnayot, is that דרך ארץ derech eretz means,
you know, proper conduct between people, good character traits, good ways of
interacting with people. So it's about just, you know, it's about your
intellectual מקרא mikra משנה mishnah or your religious, your מצוות, mitzvot, wrestling—first
we spoke about מצוות, mitzvot, now we're talking about תורה, Torah, and
now we're talking about if you want the third component of that
which would be character. Anyway, those are the things and that speaks
about that, you know, these things are as opposed to previous משנה
mishnah which is about if you do מצווה mitzvah how much you're
rewarded, here it speaks about sort of what helps you keep on
the straight and narrow, what helps you sort of keep to a
good life, you know, not good in the sense of reward but
good in the sense of like, you know, doing the right things
in life. So learning together with דרך ארץ, derech eretz, לא במהרה
הוא חוטא, lo bimhera hu chotei, you will be protected, you know,
you will not quickly sin. Recognizes that it's not a total protection
but, you know, people do sin but nevertheless it helps keep you
on the straight and narrow, okay. And if you don't have this,
then אינו מן הישוב, eino min hayishuv, like you're not even part
of, you know, normal society, like like, you know, a civilized society.
So now with that idea that we've been mentioning מצוות mitzvot and
מקרא, mikra, משנה, mishnah, דרך ארץ, derech eretz, the next stage of
the גמרא Gemara makes a lot of sense. So if you pick
up at the first narrow, at the last of the narrow lines
on מ' עמוד ב', mem amud bet, we have the
following: וכבר היו רבי טרפון וזקנים מסובים בעליית בית נתזה בלוד. ukevar
hayu Rabbi Tarfon uzekenim mesubim ba'aliyat Beit Nitzah beLud. So רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon and the elders were reclining in the attic of this
person בית נתזה Beit Nitzah in לוד, Lud, right, this almost is
like we're about to read the הגדה, Haggadah, right, about how the
rabbis were like, you know, in בני ברק. Bnei Brak. Anyway, here
they were in לוד. Lud. נשאלה זו בפניהם, nish'ela zu bifneihem, and
the following question was raised to them: תלמוד גדול או מעשה גדול?
talmud gadol o ma'aseh gadol? Which is more important, learning or doing?
Right? We spoke about the previous משנה mishnah was about מצוות, mitzvot,
this מצווה mitzvah is about learning plus דרך ארץ. derech eretz. Which
one is more weighty? Which one is more is greater than the
other? So נענה רבי טרפון ואמר מעשה גדול, na'anah Rabbi Tarfon ve'amar
ma'aseh gadol, doing is more important. נענה רבי עקיבא ואמר תלמוד גדול,
na'anah Rabbi Akiva ve'amar talmud gadol, learning is more important. נענו כולם
ואמרו, na'anu kulam ve'ameru, so then they all came to a consensus
and they said, תלמוד גדול שהתלמוד מביא לידי מעשה. talmud gadol shettalmud
meivi lidei ma'aseh. Learning is greater because learning brings to doing. So
what type of, so who won that debate, right? That's a good
thing about a compromise is that you get a consensus because you
make everybody happy. Oh, we told you תלמוד talmud was גדול gadol
but we told you that the reason תלמוד talmud was גדול gadol
was because it was מביא לידי מעשה. meivi lidei ma'aseh. Because it
brings to doing. So ultimately, right, is so it's not so clear.
It sounds actually that at some axiomatic level doing is better, right,
מעשה'ס ma'aseh's גדול, gadol, but תלמוד talmud is very weighty because it
brings it about. So it's like exactly, it's a הכשר מצווה hechsher
mitzvah that's so important. So in what way is תלמוד גדול Talmud
gadol if ultimately it's to bring about מעשה? ma'aseh? So תוספות, Tosfos,
important תוספות, Tosfos, he sort of explores this through raising a question
from another גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the תוספות: Tosfos:
תלמוד גדול שהתלמוד מביא לידי מעשה. Talmud gadol she-hatalmud meivi lidei ma'aseh.
תימה, Teimah, says תוספות, Tosfos, it's אמר בסוף פרק קמא דבבא קמא,
amar b'sof perek kamma de-Bava Kamma, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan משא ידיה
ומנח תפילין. moshi yadei u-mianach tefillin. He washed his hands after coming
out of the bathroom and put on תפילין. tefillin. והדר אמר לן,
V'hadar amar lan, and then he taught the following thing to us.
קיים Kiyyem אמרינן, amrinan, if somebody dies and they were and you
want to praise them at their הספד, hesped, what you can say
about somebody is, oh, this person fulfilled like a life of
מצוות. mitzvos. לימד Limeid לא אמרינן, lo amrinan, but we don't say
that he taught תורה, Torah, like that, you know, for a normal,
you know, person. אמרינן, Amrinan, and the גמרא Gemara says ופריך ואמר
מר u-parich ve-amar mar גדול תלמוד תורה שהתלמוד מביא לידי מעשה. gadol
talmud torah she-hatalmud meivi lidei ma'aseh. But why wouldn't we not say
that? Isn't תלמוד Talmud greater? Now what's the question? Yes, תלמוד Talmud
is greater, that's why we don't say it, because not everybody reaches
that level of תלמוד. Talmud So what was the question of the
גמרא? Gemara? We're willing to say he did מצוות, mitzvos, we're not
willing to say he like learned his whole תורה. Torah. So the
רש״י Rashi says, פירש בקונטרס, peirash b'kontras, and רש״י Rashi explains the
question of the גמרא Gemara was מי נתלה במי קטן נתלה בגדול.
Mi nitlah b'mi? Kattan nitlah b'gadol. No, that the question of the
גמרא Gemara was that since we say the only reason תלמוד Talmud.
is גדול gadol is it's מביא לידי מעשה, meivi lidei ma'aseh, that
that indicates, that betrays the fact that really מעשה ma'aseh is גדול,
gadol right? It's all about מעשה. ma'aseh. So if you're willing to
say that somebody is a בעל מעשים, ba'al ma'asim, right, is a
person of מצוות, mitzvos, why, you know, then that's you should be
willing to say that they learned תורה Torah because you're actually willing
to give the higher praise to the person. So רש״י Rashi in
that גמרא Gemara actually says our גמרא Gemara betrays the fact that
bottom line מעשה ma'aseh is really גדול. gadol, Okay? אם כן כיון
דאמר קיים כל שכן לימד וכי הוא חשוב כל כך. Im kein
keivan d'amar kiyyem, kol she-kein limeid, kein hu chashuv kol kach. אבל
מוכיח דמהכא דמעשה גדול. Aval mochiach de-meihacha de-ma'aseh gadol. So תוספות Tosfos
asks the question, from that גמרא Gemara it's clear that even if
you say תלמוד מביא לידי מעשה, Talmud meivi lidei ma'aseh, what that
shows is that מעשה ma'aseh is more important, not תלמוד's Talmud more
important. Which is it? ויש לומר דהתם הכי פירוש V'yeish lomar d'hastham
hachi peirash והדר אמר לן קיים אמרינן לימד לא אמרינן v'hadar amar
lan kiyyem amrinan limeid lo amrinan ואמר מר גדול תלמוד שהתלמוד מביא
לידי מעשה v'amar mar gadol talmud she-hatalmud meivi lidei ma'aseh אם כן
היכי קיים אם לא לימד im kein heich kiyyem im lo limeid
okay then
he has some answer which is which is confusing for us, which
I'm going to skip. Okay, and let's just skip to the line
ומשני, u-meshani, you see where it is, it's like about a third
before the תוספות Tosfos is over, beginning of a line: הא למגמר
הא לאגמורי. ha l'migmar ha l'agmurei. כלומר, Klomar, למגמר לדידיה ודאי מעשה.
l'migmar l'didei vadai ma'aseh.
If it's between your own learning or doing, then doing is more
important than your own learning. אבל לאגמורי אחריני ודאי עדיף טפי ממעשה.
Aval l'agmurei achrinei vadai adif tfei mi-ma'aseh.
That's at a higher level. לפיכך לימד לא אמרינן. L'fichach limeid lo
amrinan. So for תוספות, Tosfos, our גמרא Gemara shows that when it
comes to your own personal religious achievement, your actions are more important
than your learning. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara there that indicates that
the learning was at a higher level, right, that's teaching others. The
best is to teach others. So there's a hierarchy is the lowest
is your own just learning for yourself. The next level is doing
מצוות. mitzvos. The highest achievement, the highest form of like religious achievement
is teaching other people. Better than מצוות, mitzvos, better than yourself doing.
I mean, not that you're supposed to not do, but if you
have to choose between should I go now and do a מצוה
mitzvah or should I go now and teach a שיעור, shiur, you
should teach a שיעור. shiur. But if you have to choose between
should I go and do a מצוה mitzvah or should I go
and open and learn גמרא Gemara for myself, you go and you
do the מצוה. mitzvah. And that's one way of thinking about it.
ויש מפרשים דאדם שלא למד עדיין ובא ללמוד אם ילמד תחלה או
יעסוק במעשה. V'yeish mefarshim d'adam she-lo lamad adayin u-ba lilmod im yilmod
techilah o ya'asok b'ma'aseh. So
what he reframes the question of the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe the question
of the גמרא Gemara is somebody says, how should I like what's
the right here, Dov, you'll appreciate this, what's the right pedagogy? What's
the right course of religious education?
Should I first focus on doing more מצוות, mitzvos, or should I
first focus on learning? Okay, so it's not a question of which
sort of is
religiously axiomatically at a higher level. What's the best way to grow
in my, you know, religiously? So then we say או משום לא
למד ללמוד תחלה לפי שאין עם הארץ חסיד. O mishum lo lamad
lilmod techilah l'fi she-ein am ha-aretz chasid.
You know what? First thing you have to do is you should
really learn. You know, spend some time learning the משנה ברורה, Mishnah
Berurah, spend some time learning what you're supposed to do. You know,
and then אבל אדם שלמד כבר המעשה טוב יותר מלימוד. aval adam
she-lamad kvar ha-ma'aseh tov yoter mi-limmud.
So that still maintains obviously the hierarchy. The hierarchy is ultimately it's
about doing. Learning is a way of bringing about doing. So then
what do we mean that תלמוד Talmud is גדול? gadol. We mean
it's
גדול gadol? have that in principle doing is the best. The only
thing higher than doing is teaching. Okay, and תלמוד Talmud גדול only
means that that's a way practically of bringing it about. You know,
תלמוד Talmud brings to מעשה, ma'aseh, מעשה ma'aseh doesn't bring to תלמוד.
Talmud. Okay, so that's like a practical preference but it's not an
axiomatic preference. Now this issue, of course, as you Now this issue,
of course as you can imagine, is not something that just rested
here because certainly for people that invested their entire lives in sitting
and learning, right, and teaching, well I guess if you learn and
teach you could sort of work with תוספות. Tosfos But if you
basically like spend your entire life sitting in ישיבה Yeshiva and in
כולל Kollel all day and sitting and learning, how do you, you
know, it's obviously, and you, not just I'm not just saying it
as a self-justification, you know, there's a deep theology, you know like
we said before, תלמוד תורה כנגד כולם, Talmud Torah Keneged Kulam, the
most important thing is learning, how do you deal with this תלמוד
מביא לידי מעשה Talmud Meivi Lidey Maaseh type of an answer? By
the way, what I should say is תלמוד תורה כנגד כולם Talmud
Torah Keneged Kulam in the context of yesterday did not mean that
the most important מצוה Mitzvah to do is תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
It meant, what was the context of that
list of תלמוד תורה כנגד כולם?
Talmud Torah Keneged
Kulam?
Things that you're אוכל פירותיהן בעולם הזה. Ochel Peiroteihen Baolam Hazeh. What
it might be saying is the things that you will reap their
benefit in this world, amongst the things that you'll reap their benefit
in this world, the thing that you will most reap the benefits
for is your learning of תורה. Torah. And again, given yesterday's context,
it doesn't mean because it's the most important, it doesn't have to
mean it's because it's the most important מצוה Mitzvah and God will
reward you the most. It must mean, or it might mean exactly
like this, because תלמוד מביא לידי מעשה, Talmud Meivi Lidey Maaseh, because
that learning will translate into doing, it'll affect your character, it'll affect
your relationship to other people, right? So it might very well mean
in terms of what is אוכל פירותיהן בעולם הזה. Ochel Peiroteihen Baolam
Hazeh. So anyway, how do you deal with this if you think
that really it's all about מעשה? Maaseh? I mean how do you,
so there were definitely
ראשונים Rishonim and Jewish thinkers that did say it was fundamentally about
מעשה. Maaseh. רבינו יונה Rabbeinu Yonah says wait a minute, if it's
all about מעשה, Maaseh, why do we learn like מסכת קדשים? Masechet
Kodashim? I mean you know סדר קדשים. Seder Kodashim. Like why do
we learn all these מסכתות? Masechtos? Like Michael, you always want to
know what's the הלכה. Halacha. So that's basically, right here, why are
we learning all this stuff that doesn't translate into מעשה? Maaseh? And
the answer basically was, well, but it translates into יראת שמים, Yirat
Shamayim, and it translates into character traits. But ultimately, the answer was
not because תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is just important even without מעשה,
Maaseh, right? Or think about the line in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot,
לא המדרש הוא העיקר אלא המעשה. Lo Hamidrash Hu Haikar Ela Hamaaseh.
So there definitely is a way of thinking that ultimately really it
is about translating into a religious life. It doesn't just mean learning
הלכות תפילין, Hilchos Tefillin, like learning הלכות חמץ, Hilchos Chametz, you know
like רבינו יונה Rabbeinu Yonah says, it could be about molding character,
influencing how you look at the world, how you interact with other
people, but ultimately it's about translating into a religious life. It's not
what we call תורה לשמה, Torah Lishmah, learning for its own sake.
That definitely is what's emphasized in this גמרא. Gemara. Others felt otherwise,
and I'll just tell you how you would position a different statement
and then we'll move on, which is, first of all, let me
just talk about that line in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, לא המדרש
הוא העיקר אלא
המעשה.
Lo Hamidrash Hu Haikar Ela
Hamaaseh. The same רבינו יונה Rabbeinu Yonah who actually elsewhere, as I
said, talks about how really learning is about translating into doing, but
you know what he says that line means? לא המדרש הוא העיקר
אלא המעשה, Lo Hamidrash Hu Haikar Ela Hamaaseh, he means you do
not influence and teach people primarily by what you say. You influence
them by what you do, right? So you know the whole thing
don't do as I, you know don't do as I do, do
as I say, that doesn't work. You know, the way you teach
and influence people is much more by what you do than by
what you say. So that's just in terms of that line, very
powerful, right? And that's just in terms of that line in פרקי
אבות. Pirkei Avot. But no, but the way you would explain this
גמרא Gemara I think would be what David said, because David said
wait a minute, right? This is the problem I had when I
first heard this גמרא. Gemara. I mean learning is also a מצוה.
Mitzvah. So what you know, so what do you mean, it's like
it's between learning and doing? Learning is a form of, okay, so
it means yes, it's a form of doing, but it's a form
of, it's intellectual, it's not in the real world, it doesn't affect
other people. But nevertheless, that's a way of understanding this גמרא. Gemara.
A way of understanding this גמרא Gemara is that that's the resolution.
The resolution is which is better? And the answer is תלמוד Talmud
is better. Not because the whole purpose of learning is to bring
to doing, no, no, no. This is a מצוה Mitzvah and this
is a מצוה. Mitzvah. So which מצוה Mitzvah is better? The מצוה
Mitzvah of shaking a לולב Lulav or the מצוה Mitzvah of learning
גמרא? Gemara? They're both מצוות. Mitzvos. And the answer is oh, the
מצוה Mitzvah of learning גמרא Gemara is better because the מצוה Mitzvah
of learning גמרא Gemara is a twofer. You get two for one.
You get a מצוה Mitzvah and you get that it brings about
other מצוות, Mitzvos, right? So a way of learning this is not
the whole point of learning is to bring about doing. It's that
actually learning is intrinsically important, doing is intrinsically important, and learning has
one up on doing. Why does it have one up on doing?
Because it also brings about other doing. Shaking a לולב Lulav doesn't
mostly translate into doing other מצוות. Mitzvos. But learning is a מצוה
Mitzvah that does translate into other מצוות. Mitzvos. Okay, so there's two
very different ways of learning this גמרא. Gemara. Is it that the
whole point of learning ultimately is to shape character, translate into the
world and so on? Fundamentally it's on a lower level. Or is
the point that learning is actually starts at an equal level with
everything else and actually is better than everything else because it also
has the power to translate into other forms of doing. Okay, so
that's as you can imagine a very important גמרא Gemara in terms
of thinking about the relationship between תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and מצוות.
Mitzvos. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, תניא, Tanya, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi אומר, Omer, גדול תלמוד שקדם לחלה ארבעים שנה. Gadol Talmud shekodam
lachallah arbaim shanah. תלמוד Talmud is great that it preceded the מצוה
Mitzvah of חלה Challah for forty years. Okay, because the תורה Torah
was
Why did God have to command the מצוה mitzvah of חלה challah
if it wasn't going to be done for the next forty years?
So what it shows you is that ultimately either A you could
say you could learn independent of doing, but also what I think
it is, ultimately the learning precedes the doing. Right? The learning ultimately
comes as a way of preparing yourself for the doing. So תלמוד
Talmud the תורה Torah came 40 years before חלה challah began to
be practiced. לתרומות ומעשרות חמשים וארבע, le-trumos u-maasros chamishim ve-arba,
54 years between תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-maasros because תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-maasros
didn't begin until the 14 years after they had entered the land
and conquered and settled it. לשמיטין ששים ואחת, le-shmitin shishim ve-achas, for
שמיטה, shmita, 61 years. It began after 14 years after entering the
land, that's 54, and then you start counting, seven years later is
שמיטה, shmita, 61. ליובלות מאה ושלש, le-yovelos me'ah ve-shalosh,
and for יובל Yovel 103 years, because you started counting after 54,
40 of getting into the land, 14 after settling, then you started,
and then יובל Yovel began on year 103. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאה ושלש מאה וארבע הויין, me'ah ve-shalosh me'ah ve-arba havyan, the
end of the 50th year is only on 104. No, but קסבר
יובל מתחילתו הוא משמיט. kasavar yovel mi-techilaso hu mashmit. Yes, but the
freeing of the slaves and the returning of the land, that all
starts at the beginning of יובל, Yovel, so the effect of the
יובל Yovel happened at the beginning of the יובל, Yovel, which means
after 49 years as opposed to after 50 years, because after 49
the 50th year began. Okay. וכשם שהלימוד קודם למעשה, u-keshem she-halimud kodem
le-ma'aseh, and the same way learning preceded the doing, כך דינו קודם
למעשה, kach dino kodem le-ma'aseh, the judgment of if you slacken in
your learning, you'll be judged first for that than for slackening in
your doing of מצוות. mitzvos. כדרב המנונא דאמר רב המנונא אין תחילת
דינו של אדם אלא על דברי תורה. ki-de-Rav Hamnuna d'amar Rav Hamnuna
ein techilas dino shel adam ela al divrei Torah. The first thing
you're judged for is about your learning of תורה. Torah. שנאמר פוטר
מים ראשית מדון. she-ne'emar peter mayim reshish madon. So מים mayim is
תורה Torah here and the way רש"י Rashi says if you exempt
yourself from water if you sort you do not shirk your obligations
relating to תורה Torah that'll be the first thing you're judged for.
וכשם שדינו קודם למעשה u-keshem she-dino kodem le-ma'aseh what does
it mean
פשט p'shat פוטר מים ראשית מדון? peter mayim reshish madon?
I don't know. Okay. Whatever. It's a hard translation. I want to
move on. וכשם שדינו קודם למעשה כך שכרו קודם למעשה, u-keshem she-dino
kodem le-ma'aseh kach scharo kodem le-ma'aseh, and the same way you will
be judged negatively, you will be rewarded first for תלמוד Talmud before
for your doings. שנאמר ויתן להם ארצות גוים ועמל לאומים יירשו, she-ne'emar
va-yiten lahem artzos goyim va-amal le'umim yirashu, God will give and He
gave them the lands of the nations and they inherited the labor
of the nations. בעבור ישמרו חוקיו, ba-avur yishmeru chukav, because they observed
His commandments, ותורותיו ינצורו, ve-sorosav yintzoru, and they protected His תורה. Torah.
Now how does that show that it's for the doing? You could
say ישמרו חוקיו yishmeru chukav means that they observed they did the
מצוות, mitzvos, but it seems that the idea of protecting, observing,
guarding, the way you guard a life of תורה ומצוות Torah u-mitzvos
is through the learning. All right, but still it does seem within
all of this that it's still operating within the matrix of learning
bringing about doing. Protecting the מצוות mitzvos is through the learning, but
it still seems that much in this very much like tight connection
as opposed to like a type of a theology of pure תורה
לשמה. Torah lishmah. Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues.
קודם למעשה kodem le-ma'aseh would I thought still that the מעשה ma'aseh
would you be judged for first?
Well,
so that's the thing. Do you say that because you're judged first
that shows that it's more important? Like the simple read of the
גמרא? Gemara? Or do you say you're judged for it first because
ultimately it's the gateway and it translates into everything
else? So that's the question. It seems here the constant sense of
first before this seems not like they're completely unrelated things and this
is more important. It seems like they're very tightly related things and
this is the one that comes first because it brings the other
thing about. That's I think the sense of this גמרא. Gemara.
You understand the difference that I'm saying, right? It's not saying like
well I would have to think about a context. Are you going
to be judged first for
תפילין tefillin or for
לולב? lulav? It's not that sense that they're completely unrelated. It seems
like I mean the very פסוק pasuk about ותורותיו ינצורו ישמרו חוקיו
torosav yintzoru yishmeru chukav seems like it's not just oh well A
is more important than B. It's that they are related and one
leads to the other and the one that leads to the other
is the one that you're judged for first and rewarded for first.
Right. Now again, it doesn't mean it's only purpose is that. It
could be that it has equal value separate from that and additional
value because it brings about the other as well.
In which case then you can say overall it's more important.
Right, exactly, exactly. So that's the big question of this גמרא. Gemara.
כל שאינו לא במקרא ולא במשנה ולא בדרך ארץ. kol she-eino lo
be-mikra ve-lo be-mishnah ve-lo be-derech eretz. So it says אמר רבי יוחנן
ופסול לעדות, amar Rabbi Yochanan u-pasul le-eidus, somebody who is not connected
to a life of learning and I would sort of say religious
connection, observance, doesn't learn in terms of הלכה, halacha, doesn't learn anything
religious and דרך ארץ derech eretz which could mean a פרנסה parnassah
or could mean doesn't have any decent character traits. So that person
is so much at the outskirts of society that you can't trust
their testimony.
And what do we mean...
Yes, we pass, I mean whatever, מדרבנן. mi-d'rabanan. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, האוכל בשוק הרי זה דומה לכלב, Ha-ochel ba-shuk harey ze domeh
l'kelev, if you eat in the marketplace you're like a dog, ויש
אומרים v'yesh omrim because that's what dogs do, they eat in public,
פסול לעדות, pasul l'edus, that somebody who doesn't appreciate certain sense of
norms of society and norms of behavior and polite society whatever, is
somebody that you just generally can't trust them to their morals, which
is an interesting question. Yeah, now by the way the מהרש"א Maharsha
says he can't believe that it really means just because you eat
in public, and the מהרש"א Maharsha says it means sort of like
if you
grab stuff off of the fruit stand and eat it. Of course
then he says you're just סתם א גזלן, stam a gazlan, so
anyway.
Alright, ויש אומרים פסול לעדות. v'yesh omrim pasul l'edus. אמר רבי אידי
בר אבין הלכה כיש אומרים, Amar Rabbi Idi bar Avin halacha k'yesh
omrim, rule that way. דרש בר קפרא, Darash Bar Kappara, רגזן, ragzan,
because we're talking about the way the מהרש"א Maharsha understands דרך ארץ,
derech eretz, which could be meant as character traits, so and this
also a little bit fits in the סוגיא sugya discussion before about
אוכל פירותיהם בעולם הזה, ochel peiroteihem ba-olam ha-zeh, and remember we talked
before about an עבירה aveira that's עושה פרי oseh pri and a
מצווה mitzvah that's עושה פרי, oseh pri, so let's see what he
says. רגזן, Ragzan, somebody who's always getting angry, לא עלתה בידו אלא
רגזנותו. lo alta b'yado ela ragzanuto. All you gain from your anger
was your anger, meaning it's
not it doesn't produce anything of value, right, it's not עושה פרי
oseh pri or the פרי pri it makes is an ulcer, right,
the פרי pri it makes is like you get yourself high blood
pressure. That's all your anger is going to produce. Okay, לאדם טוב,
l'adam tov, but a good person, מטיעימין אותו מפרי מעשיו, mati'imin oto
mipri ma'asav, again you get the fruit of their labor. So before
we talked about the מצוות, mitzvos, here we're talking more about your
character, your character produces positive fruit or negative fruit. Okay, וכל שאינו
לא במקרא ולא במשנה ולא בדרך ארץ, v'chol she-eino lo b'Mikra v'lo
b'Mishnah v'lo b'derech eretz, דור הנאה ממנו. dur hana'ah mimenu. If somebody
is doesn't involved in any sense of learning and again either
good character or if you say involved in a פרנסה, parnassah, so
they have no worthwhile pursuits, then you should be מודר הנאה mudar
hana'ah from him, you should make a נדר neder that you can't
get הנאה hana'ah from him, he can't get הנאה hana'ah from you,
so that'll keep you very far away from him. And how do
you why?
שנאמר ובמושב לצים לא ישב, shene'emar u-v'moshav leitzim lo yashav, right, מושב,
moshav, ובמושב לצים, u-v'moshav leitzim, because wherever he will be it will
be a community of mockers. If somebody doesn't have a job and
doesn't spend his time learning תורה, Torah, what do you spend your
time doing? You're wasting it on trivial pursuits, you're wasting it on,
so this type of a person is a bad
influence and only wastes his time doing unworthy things. So better just
really, really keep your distance from such a person. Okay, so very
fascinating פרק perek starting with קידושין, Kiddushin, going on to קניינים, kinyanim,
going on to מצוות, mitzvos, ending with an issue about general character
traits, right, and really I think the beautiful thing about the end
is about how we can reap our rewards in this world and
you sort of see that in terms of very practically what our
מצוות mitzvos and character produces,
and it's not just limited to a sense of like how God
will reward us in the world to come. הדרן עלך האשה נקנית.
Hadran alach ha-ishah nikneis. Phew, so that was some big פרק. perek.
Now we move on to the next פרק, perek, let's see what
we got. הדרן עלך, Hadran alach, exactly. Let's move on to the
next פרק, perek, which gets us back to קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay, and
you might be surprised to find out ties us directly in not
only to פסח Pesach but
to ערב פסח. erev Pesach. Okay, ready for some? We'll start it
today and we'll continue it tomorrow. האיש מקדש בו ובשלוחו. Ha-ish mekadesh
bo u-v'shlucho. A man מקדש, mekadesh, notice now we've completely dropped the
language of קניין kinyan as the גמרא Gemara points out that was
לישנא דקרא. lishnah d'kra. Now we're in the rabbinic concept of it
which is קידושין. Kiddushin. A man marries a woman directly or through
his agent. האשה מתקדשת בה ובשלוחה. Ha-ishah miskadeshet bah u-v'shluchah. A woman
can be betrothed directly by receiving the money herself or through an
agent. האיש מקדש את בתו כשהיא נערה בו ובשלוחו. Ha-ish mekadesh es
bito k'she-hi na'arah bo u-v'shlucho.
And the same way a man has the right, a father has
the right to marry off his daughter, it's interesting, it's like starts
as a קטנה, k'tanah, but even through the age of נערה, na'arah,
okay he can marry her off, he can do it directly and
he can do it through an agent. Alright, so which is a
big חידוש chiddush because you might think he's not the principal there,
he's representing his daughter, maybe he can't make an agent to do
that for him. Right.
Why is it such a huge why is it simply important to
us introduce the category that's only six months in duration? Is it
because of the onset of physical maturity? In other words, the קטנה
k'tanah and the בוגרת. bogeres.
Well, I mean, it's in the תורה. Torah. I think that the
point is is that פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is that
you don't have this six months duration. פשט Pshat of the פסוקים
psukim is who knows how long נערה na'arah lasts. נערה Na'arah could
last as long as while she once she reaches some sense of
maturity until she gets married off, like I don't know. חז"ל Chazal
understood that it was a briefer period of time, but and then
the reason it gets developed in הלכה halacha is because it's all
the everywhere in the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah everywhere talks about
בנעוריה בית אביה, b'neureha beis aviha, so the obviously הלכה's halacha going
to explore that status. I mean, you could talk about it more
philosophically, but the פשט pshat reason is is just because it's everywhere
in the תורה. Torah. If you want to say why is it
everywhere in the תורה, Torah, probably because in the פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim probably don't have it just as a six months
type of a limit. Or you could say maybe if they do,
maybe it was the
critical period where she was of marriageable age and she was getting
married. off that was when every single thing was happening, that was
the transition period. The key also is that that’s the sort of
gray period and the transition period as well.
It’s so, it’s so extant, right? It’s fascinating that it’s so formalistically
narrow too.
I understand, I yeah okay. Alright, let’s take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. השתא בשלוחו מקדש, hashta bishlucha mekadesh,
if he can marry through an agent, בו מיבעיא, bo mibaya, of
course you can marry yourself through your, you know, you can do
it yourself. Of course, the simple answer is that’s just a literary
way of saying it, right? You know, not only בו, bo, even
בשלוחו bishlucha or whatever, you know. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara wants
to ask, why did you have to say בו bo once you
said, once you’re going to say שלוחו? shlucha? So אמר רב יוסף,
amar rav yosef, מצוה בו יותר מבשלוחו, mitzvah bo yoser mibishlucha, to
tell you it’s preferable to do it yourself, okay. And this becomes
a general concept, not just a קידושין kiddushin concept. You know, even
though some מצוות mitzvot you can do, some מצוות mitzvot you have
to do yourself, like taking the לולב. lulav. Other מצוות, mitzvot, you
know, you could do in theory through somebody else, like בדיקת חמץ
bdikas chametz is a good example. I can hire somebody to check
check it. Nevertheless, we say it’s better to do it yourself. כי
הא דרב ספרא מחריך רישא, ki ha derav safra machrich resha, רב
ספרא rav safra would like char the head of a fish or
whatever, maybe of a of a sheep anyway, for שבת, shabbos, he
would do a little שבת shabbos preparations. רבא מלח שיבוטא, rava malach
shibuta, רבא rava would salt the salt the fish, you know. Even
these great rabbis would go ahead and do a little stuff, I
mean, you know, their wives would be spending the whole day cooking,
but they would at least spend some of the time doing something,
right, to participate in the מצוה mitzvah of כבוד שבת kvod shabbos
directly.
They say משלוח מנות mishloach manot though, they
say some people want to do it דווקא. davka. Well, that’s because
of the framing of משלוח mishloach anyway, and that might have to
do with anyway whatever. Now what is the reason to do it
personally? So look at רש"י, Rashi, right? I mean, you’re getting the
מצוה mitzvah done. So רש"י Rashi says מצוה בו יותר מבשלוחו, mitzvah
bo yoser mibishlucha, דכי עסיק גופיה במצוה מקבל שכר טפי. dechi asi
gufa bemitzvot mekabel schar tvei. So you could say that רש"י Rashi
is just talking sort of like the previous גמרא, Gemara, well, you
know, you get more brownie points because you exert more effort, so
you deserve to be rewarded more because you exerted more effort, okay.
But I would, but I would emphasize like we’re talking about what
it means אוכל פירותיהם, ochel peroseyhem, that this doesn’t just mean God
will reward you because you did a little bit more effort. He’s
saying עסיק גופו במצוות, asi gufo bemitzvot, you know, that when you
personally do something it impacts you in a different way, right? If
you exert the effort of כבוד שבת, kvod shabbos, it’s not like
oh I spent effort to do it, I deserve to be rewarded.
You connect to שבת shabbos in a different way, it’s more real
to you, right? It’s in your קישקעס kishkes more, right? That’s what
it means to to personally engage with your very body in the
מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so therefore that we’re gonna say the same thing
here. So that’s why better to do it yourself. איכא דאמרי, ika
deamri, but some say when it comes to the man, בהא איסורא
נמי אית בה, behai issura nami isba, for him to not do
it personally, not just would not be ideal, but to not do
it personally would actually be a degree of an איסור. issur. What
would be the איסור issur to not do it personally? כי דרב
יהודה אמר רב, ke de rav yehuda amar rav, like רב יהודה
אמר רב, rav yehuda amar rav, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, damar
rav yehuda amar rav, אסור לאדם שיקדש אשה עד שיראנה. assur leadam
sheyekadesh isha ad sheyirena. You cannot betroth a woman until you’ve seen
her, right? You could see her and then not do the act
personally, correct. This is reflecting an assumption
that betrothal would often happen, right, not after a period of dating
or whatever. It was like I would say to you, hey, you
know what, go find me a woman in that other town, it’s
time for me to get married, okay. So that would obviously שלוחו
shlucha could just be the act is done through an agent and
you yourself know the woman you’re marrying. Alright, yes, anyway. But the
גמרא Gemara sort of says if we if you read שלוחו shlucha
could include cases where you don’t even know the woman, then it’s
much better for you to do it personally. Now not saying that
you have to go through a period of dating, okay, but it’s
better to do it personally חס ושלום, chas veshalom, okay, ביטול תורה.
bittel torah. But
but as long as you’re doing it personally, at least you get
a moment to look at her and to decide are you attracted
to her, whatever, even if it’s just for those two minutes before
you decide to go through with it. One minute, אסור לאדם שיקדש
אשה עד שיראנה, assur leadam sheyekadesh isha ad sheyirena, שמא יראה בה
דבר מגונה, shema yireh bah davar maguneh, lest after you’re already married
to her you’ll find something that is displeasing, it’s more of a
visceral word than displeasing, repulsive, ותתגנה עליו, veyitganeh aleha, and then she’ll
be repulsive to you. ורחמנא אמר ואהבת לרעך כמוך, ve rachmana amar
veahavta lereacha kamocha, love your neighbor as yourself, and therefore it would
be really bad not to have you know that that’s the way
you would feel about your wife. Now I have to tell you,
you know, for a long time I read this and it really
sort of left me feeling a little flat, like the only reason
that you know you have to feel attraction or whatever, feel positive
towards your wife is ואהבת לרעך כמוך, veahavta lereacha kamocha, the same
way I have to feel nice towards you I have to feel
nice towards my wife or whatever, you know. So where’s the greater
sense obviously of like a deeper emotional connection? But through a different
lens, you know, you have to acknowledge that the גמרא Gemara is
dealing with a time when a lot of people got married having
nothing to do with an emotional connection. The very fact that we’re
talking about a scenario where you send an agent or the first
time you’re seeing your wife is under the חופה chuppah when you
come to give her the ring, right? So if that’s the reality
that we’re dealing with people that the first time they would see
the woman would be you know when they would give her the
ring and we’re telling you oh, don’t do it through an agent,
have a moment to see her when Not talking about a society
in which marriage is about a deep emotional connection, right? And nevertheless,
what it realizes is that once you're married, even in a time
when you could divorce, you know, unilaterally or whatever, I mean there
would still be the כתובה ketubah payment. Once people are married, they
don't quickly get divorced even if things aren't perfect, right? And very
often, you know, people stay in marriage when things are very... are
very imperfect, are very difficult. So then, you know, so then there
is something very profound in that type of place where people are
getting married for more practical, less romantic, less emotional reasons, to still
say like it is a really bad phenomenon if you're stuck with
somebody and you... and you, you know, and there's such of this
like a, you know, this like repulsion between you. Like, you know,
and minimally, even if she's not like the love of your life,
she's still a fellow person, right? And, you know, and what does
it mean to actually be able to have, you know, so that
sense of... this is... אהבה ahava here is not the romantic love
of marriage. It's genericized to ואהבת לרעך כמוך. ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha. But
again, I still think there's something very profound that even in a
reality in which that's what marriage is, that it's not romantic and
it's not deeply emotional or whatever, it's like you really have to,
like, you know, connect and get along and, you know, feel positively
towards the other person. Good point.
Yes. But you can read it the opposite way, because it says
that רע reya means beloved, not just fellow person.
Maybe. So maybe they're choosing to read it in that more narrow
way. But again, it's not talking about emotional love, it's talking about
you shouldn't find your wife repulsive. Okay, right? So, you know, so
it's not like imagining like the couple can't remain married for forty
years, or couples are married for forty years and hate each other's
guts, you know? I'm serious, right? So it's not like, oh my
god, lest you get divorced, lest this. It's just deeply problematic, you
know, even if you'll stay married and have kids or whatever, externally
everything is right, like there's that point of... Anyway, so I think
there is, given a society in which we... is not prizing romantic
love, it's an important statement. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
וכי אתמר דרב יוסף, vechi itmar deRav Yosef, and when was רב
יוסף Rav Yosef said? אסיפא אתמר. a seifa itmar. That is,
it's not just that it's just a מצוה mitzvah to do it
personally, but it's not that it would be an איסור issur to
do it through a שליח. shaliach. So that was on the end
of the משנה. Mishnah. האישה מתקדשת בה ובשלוחה, ha'ishah mitkadeshet bah uveshlucha,
a woman is married personally or through her agent. השתא בשלוחה מקדשא
בה מיבעיא, hata bishlucha mekadesha bah miba'ya, if she can do it
through an agent, certainly she could do it herself. אמר רב יוסף
מצוה בה יותר מבשלוחה. amar Rav Yosef mitzvah bah yoteir mibishlucha. No,
it's better to do it personally than to do it through her
agent. כי הא דרב ספרא מחריך רישי רבא מלח שיבוטא, ke'ha deRav
Safra machrich reishei Rava malach shibuta, like we said before, better to
do the מצוות mitzvot personally. אבל בה, aval beha, but for her,
to choose to do it through an agent, איסור לית בה. issur
leit bah. If she were to do it through an agent, she
would not actually be doing anything wrong. It wouldn't be ideal, but
she wouldn't be doing anything wrong. Why? Why aren't we afraid of
ואהבת לרעך כמוך ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha on her end? She doesn't see
the guy she's about to marry. כי דריש לקיש, kideReish Lakish, דאמר
ריש לקיש טב למיתב טן דו מלמיתב ארמלו, de'amar Reish Lakish tav
lemeitav tan du milemeitav armelu, the famous statement of ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, better to sit in tandem than to sit, like, you know,
than to live as a widow or, you know, to live alone.
So that basically the presumption that women are willing to settle much
more than men. Okay, and therefore, and therefore, when...
even if she finds her husband a little ugly and a little
repulsive, she's not going to be, you know, there's not going to
be as much of, you know, there's not going to be as
much of a sense of like repulsion and, you know, antagonism and
so on, you know, than in the reverse. So again, this is
reflecting a certain societal reality. Some people will... might claim that, you
know, that there's truth to that even till today.
But, you know, but whatever it is, this is why the גמרא
Gemara sort of says that for from his end... The interesting thing
is how this translates into not just sort of sociological statements, but
into sometimes halakhic issues around עגונה, agunah, you know, and a lack
of a certain motivation to be proactive around עגונה agunah issues because
of a presumption that women are more okay with less than perfect
situations and they can tolerate it more and so on, you know?
So there are problematics associated with this. Anyway, but nevertheless this is
the point, that for a man, if he's not happy with his
wife, you know, he looks at her later and he doesn't find
her attractive, that's going to lead to a much worse marital dynamics
than in the reverse. So for her it's a מצוה, mitzvah, for
him it would be an איסור issur to do otherwise. So very...
a lot of interesting insight into the nature of marriage, it's not
exactly romantic, a read of men and women and so on, that
comes through this גמרא. Gemara. Now I want to say two other
important things about this. Number one is, what is this whole idea
of מצוה? mitzvah? There's a מצוה. mitzvah. We haven't been focusing on
a מצוה mitzvah to get married, we've been focusing on the legal
institution of
קידושין.
kiddushin. Well, look at the previous סוגיות, sugyas, it's a continuation of
the previous...
That's not my question. My question is, why are we presuming marriage
is a מצוה, mitzvah, right? If we talked about buying a ship,
buying a boat, right? Talked... look at the קניין kinyan lens. Okay,
well, better to buy a boat yourself through... yourself than through an
agent because מצוה בו יותר מבשלוחה. mitzvah bo yoteir mibishlucho. Who was
ever talking about a מצוה, mitzvah, right? I'm buying a boat, I'm
buying a wife, I'm getting married, it's an institution, who made it
into a מצוה? mitzvah? So this... well, okay, so this raises an
important question in the ראשונים, Rishonim, which is... Is getting married a
מצוה mitzvah or not? Okay, and the, a lot of ראשונים Rishonim
say it isn't.
The, some ראשונים Rishonim say it's a מצוה mitzvah as a הכשר
מצוה hechshir mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru urvu. Okay, so and that
actually fits very nicely in the parallel with כבוד שבת. kavod Shabbos.
Right, כבוד שבת kavod Shabbos is not exactly a מצוה mitzvah in
the תורה, Torah, but it is a way of getting of making
a nice שבת, Shabbos, it's a type of a הכשר מצוה. hechshir
mitzvah. We learn it from דברי נביאים, divrei Neviim, right? But from
the תורה Torah perspective, it's a way of, it's a preparing for
the מצוה mitzvah of the תורה Torah of שבת, Shabbos, right, which
is the analogy the גמרא Gemara has.
Gozey, this is about until you're preparing for it?
Yeah, but that's like נתפרש על ידי הנביאים, nitparesh al yedei haNeviim,
it's not really seen as a דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, it's really seen as
מדברי סופרים, mi'divrei Sofrim, okay? So anyway, so that's a very nice
way of this as a parallel, as a lead to פרו ורבו
pru urvu and that's the type of מצוה mitzvah that we're talking
about.
But not a מצוה mitzvah per se.
Not a מצוה mitzvah per se. Other so some say it's not
a מצוה mitzvah at all, most who say it's a מצוה mitzvah
say it's a הכשר מצוה hechshir mitzvah for פרו ורבו. pru urvu.
There's a very complicated read of the רמב"ם. Rambam. רמב"ם Rambam says
it's a מצוה, mitzvah, it's not exactly clear what he means. He's
been interpreted to mean הכשר מצוה hechshir mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru
urvu. He's been the, by the way, the counterargument against הכשר מצוה
hechshir mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru urvu is that the ראש Rosh
says that who says you're יוצא yotzei פרו ורבו pru urvu even
if you have a child out of marriage? You're יוצא yotzei פרו
ורבו pru urvu even if it's a ממזר. mamzer. So it's not
a הכשר מצוה hechshir mitzvah for פרו ורבו, pru urvu, although when
רמב"ם Rambam discusses the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, pru urvu, רמב"ם
Rambam says there's a מצוה, mitzvah, מצוה mitzvah number one is to
get married and מצוה mitzvah number two is to have children with
your wife. So he actually frames the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו
pru urvu as a man having children with his wife. Now would
the רמב"ם Rambam say you're not יוצא yotzei if you have children
out of marriage? Not clear. But certainly primarily for him it's a
מצוה mitzvah of having children within marriage. Okay, similar, now so anyway,
so for רמב"ם Rambam what is the מצוה mitzvah of getting married?
Is it a מצוה mitzvah to enable פרו ורבו? pru urvu? Or
some say it's really not as much of a מצוה, mitzvah, it's
more of an איסור. issur. For the רמב"ם Rambam it's an איסור
issur to have sex outside of marriage. So the the מצוה mitzvah
to get married is if you're going to have sex, it better
be with, you have to get married, it has to be within
marriage. Okay, that doesn't work so much here to say מצוה בו
יותר מבשלוחו mitzvah bo yoser mibishlucho if it's only a way of
avoiding the איסור issur of having sex outside of marriage. By the
way, רמב"ם Rambam has really good Republican values. Sex is only in
marriage, kids are only in marriage. I'm serious, you know? There, because
those questions are real questions in the ראשונים, Rishonim, בהלכה bahalakhic is
all of that true? But that's the way the רמב"ם Rambam frames
it. The third possibility in the רמב"ם Rambam is that that
the מצוה mitzvah of marriage is is more that if you're going
to be married, because of the חידוש chiddush of the תורה, Torah,
the רמב"ם Rambam emphasizes that there's a חידוש chiddush in the תורה
Torah that marriage is a two-step process. You don't just jump right
and start living together a married life. First you have קידושין, kiddushin,
then you have נישואין. nisuin. Right, the רמב"ם Rambam makes a big
deal about this. Before the תורה Torah came along, you would go
straight to living together, whereas the תורה Torah comes along, before you
start living together you have קידושין kiddushin first. Now why is that
important that it be a two-step process? The רמב"ם Rambam doesn't spell
out. I've said to my students that I think what the רמב"ם
Rambam is saying is is that if you went straight to the
living reality of marriage, the living together without having the קידושין kiddushin
prior, it would basically emphasize that marriage is defined by the by
the, no, not by just producing kids, but it's defined by the
reality of the relationship. And you know, sometimes marriages hits tough spots
and the people and the they're not, you know, in terms of
right now the, you know, the marriage might not be, you know,
might really be like, you know, not doing so well in terms
of the real world, you know, what's currently true about the marriage.
But if you come with a sense of a prior commitment and
a contract that precedes the marriage, right, that precedes the living together,
it doesn't mean that you can't get divorced if you need to,
but it just means that you know, you you work through it,
you try to work through it, there's a sense of commitment to
the relationship that somewhat existed prior to the lived reality of the
relationship. So when the lived reality of the relationship is challenged, you
still have that commitment that you're and you still try to work,
you know, see if it can transcend that and survive that. Anyway,
the רמב"ם Rambam makes a big deal of the two stages. So
the other way of understanding the רמב"ם's Rambam position that there's a
מצוה mitzvah to get married is what he means is when you
want to get married, like you the מצוה mitzvah is to do
it in the order of the תורה, Torah, to understand that first
is a קידושין kiddushin and then there's a נישואין, nisuin, and to
go through those stages, to do the sort of institution that the
תורה Torah set up. Okay, but not, it's hard to imagine that
any of those last two, because those two more talk about like
structurally, you know, that that you get the idea of a מצוה
בו יותר מבשלוחו. mitzvah bo yoser mibishlucho. The language of מצוה בו
יותר מבשלוחו, mitzvah bo yoser mibishlucho, you know, works much better in
the context of a type of a הכשר מצוה hechshir mitzvah of
פרו ורבו. pru urvu. Okay, and then again, the parallel to כבוד
שבת kavod Shabbos works nicely. The other interesting question about that is
that why is it said by the women as well? Since פרו
ורבו pru urvu is a מצוה mitzvah the way the גמרא Gemara
פוסק paskens on the man and not on the woman. Okay, so
it might just be using מצוה בו יותר מבשלוחו mitzvah bo yoser
mibishlucho in a much looser and non-technical term. But this גמרא Gemara
leads to a whole. lead to, it’s part of a larger debate
of whether marriage is considered a מצוה mitzvah or not. Dov, you
have a question that you want to ask?
It’s as if I understand that it’s an opportunity for all right,
you know, those questions, but it also if לא טוב היות האדם
לבדו Lo Tov Heiyot HaAdam LeVado doesn’t factor into the discussion, right,
it points to the limitation over of overly legalistic terminology, right? In
other words, they take it as an opportunity to ask these very
important structural questions.
Right, right, right.
But ultimately, it’s so that a human being’s
life—I mean, I think that that’s beautiful and I really appreciate that.
I mean, in the גמרא Gemara in יבמות Yevamot when it speaks
about this, it says if a person, you know, has kids, you
know, has already done the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, Peru U'rvu,
should he still be married? And so one opinion is like, yeah,
you should still be married because you should still try to have
more kids. Or yeah, you should still be married because you shouldn’t
have הרהורי עבירה. Hirhurei Aveirah. But one answer is, yes, you should
still be married or like if a person’s wife died or whatever
after and he’s had kids, because לא טוב היות האדם לבדו. Lo
Tov Heiyot HaAdam LeVado. Because what do you mean? Because that basic
fundamental value of living a life with another person. So you’re right,
meaning those issues are explored absolutely, but you’re right they—that’s not part
of this formal terminology of is it a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, one
last thing just to point out because this is so rich, but
then is the תוספות, Tosafos. if you look at the תוספות Tosafot,
where it
says אסור לאדם שיקדש את בתו כשהיא—oh Asur LeAdam SheYekadesh Et Bito
KesheHi we didn’t get to that yet. Next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, האיש
מקדש את בתו כשהיא נערה. HaIsh Mekadesh Et Bito KesheHi Na’arah. A
man marries—can marry his daughter off when she’s a נערה, na’arah, either
himself or through an agent. כשהיא נערה אין כשהיא קטנה לא. KesheHi
Na'arah in, KesheHi Ketanah lo. What, does that only when she’s a
נערה? na’arah? Now logically it would say meaning even when she’s a
נערה, na’arah, obviously when she’s a minor he has total control over
her. But even when she’s a נערה na’arah and has some independence
he can still marry her off. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
no, the language of the משנה Mishnah sounds like only when she’s
a נערה. na’arah. Now of course legally he can do it when
she’s a קטנה. ketanah. But what the משנה Mishnah is doing is
it’s telling you he shouldn’t be doing it when she’s a קטנה.
ketanah. Why not? מסייע ליה לרב, Mesayyei Leih LeRav, this supports רב.
Rav. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב ואיתימא רבי אלעזר, DeAmar Rav Yehudah
Amar Rav, Ve’itayma Rabbi Elazar,
אסור לאדם שיקדש את בתו כשהיא קטנה. Asur LeAdam SheYekadesh Et Bito
KesheHi Ketanah. It’s forbidden for a man to marry off his daughter
when she’s a minor. Why? עד שתגדל ותאמר בפלוני אני רוצה. Ad
SheTigdal VeTomar BiPloni Ani Rotzah. Until she grows up and she says,
you know, I want to marry this guy. Okay, so therefore right,
so she grows up to the age of twelve. Anyway, so therefore
it’s forbidden to do it because she might not like the guy
that she marries. Now of course תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question.
Why do you use לשון אסור? lashon assur? A minute ago you
said that a woman can marry a guy, never see him, and
that wouldn’t be an איסור issur because she’ll settle. Okay, so תוספות
Tosafot says no, this is a big difference. When the woman is
an adult, maybe twelve, but an adult, and says I am prepared
to make an agent and marry whoever my agent agrees to, so
you’ve you’ve agreed to it. You’ve made your peace with marrying whoever
the agent will marry for you. And then we’ll say even if
she’s not—even if he’s not great, you’ll you’ll be prepared to settle.
Okay, more than a man would be even if he thinks he’s
ready to settle. Okay, but in this case, she’s a minor. She
never agreed to marry—to have somebody do it for her. She never
said that she’d be prepared for anybody that she—that you know, that
her agent would find out. So in this case if you don’t
have her already agreeing to that, to being prepared to settle and
be okay with it, then it’s אסור. assur. Then we’re also afraid
that the woman’s end—the woman also, you know. So that’s interesting. It’s
not like a סתם stam case where we say a woman will
settle for anyone. If a woman says she’ll—she’ll settle, then we trust
that she will settle. That was the case before. She said she’d
settle. She said whoever the agent finds. If she didn’t say that,
then we have to assume that she also won’t be happy with
some random guy. And that’s אסור לקדש את אשתו עד שיראנו. Asur
LeKadesh Et Ishto Ad SheYirenu. Now one more thing תוספות Tosafot says
אסור לאדם שיקדש
את בתו—oh
Asur LeAdam
SheYekadesh
Et Bito sorry את בתו כשהיא קטנה. Et Bito KesheHi Ketanah. Now
if you look at תוספות, Tosafot by the way, it’s an interesting
question whether we learn it out from רבקה. Rivkah. Because by רבקה
Rivkah it says נשאלה לנערה ונשאלה את פיה, Nish’alah LaNa’arah VeNish’alah Et
Piha, right?
So let’s ask her. So רש"י Rashi there says, I think, that
it’s אסור assur for a woman to be—to do נשואין nissuin
until she’s ready to do—whatever anyway. So but that certainly seems like
a—here we’re talking about קידושין, kiddushin, but that certainly seems like a
parallel. By the way, and now look at תוספות, Tosafot, אסור לאדם
שיקדש את בתו קטנה. Asur LeAdam SheYekadesh Et Bito Ketanah. The end
of תוספות Tosafot, says ועכשיו שאנו נוהגים, Ve’Achshav SheAnu Nohagin,
there’s like a little ב bet in parentheses at the beginning of
a line. ועכשיו שאנו נוהגים לקדש בנותינו אפילו קטנות, Ve’Achshav SheAnu Nohagin
LeKadesh Benoteinu Afillu Ketanot, but we do it now, we marry off
our daughters even when they’re minors. היינו משום שבכל יום ויום הגלות
מתגבר עלינו. Haynu Mishum SheBeChol Yom VeYom HaGalut Mitgaber Aleinu.
Every day like, you know, the—the גלות, galut, the exile, but it
means obviously, you know, the Crusades and right, the oppression. ואם יש
סיפק ביד אדם עכשיו לתת לבתו נדוניה. Ve’Im Yesh Sipek BeYad Adam
Achshav Latet LeBito Nedunyah. And
if right now you can give your daughter a dowry, שמא לאחר
זמן לא יהיה סיפק בידו ותשב בתו עגונה לעולם. Shema Le’Achar Zeman
Lo Yiheyeh Sipek BeYado VeTeshev Bito Agunah LeOlam. So you marry off
your daughter when you’re able to marry her off and ensure her
future, ensure that a man will take care of her and protect
her and, you know, that obviously has to have priority.
All right, so yes, so I’m trying to square that away with
עמי וריה, Ami Veriah, which is the idea is to do ייחוד,
yihud, right? But if she’s not supposed to מקדש mekadesh her when
she’s קטנה, ketanah, then—well,
I mean it’s not just—I mean there’s a good point about עמי
וריה, Ami Veriah, but it’s not just עמי וריה, Ami Veriah, it’s
like... Here you have a phenomenon that exists completely throughout the תורה
*Torah* about marrying off, right? נתתי את בתי לאיש הזה *Natati Et
Biti La'ish Hazeh*, whatever, no, all these things about marrying off a
daughter. And חז"ל *Chazal* say, oh, all that stuff you see in
the תורה *Torah*, it's really אסור *Assur* to do לכתחילה *Lechatchila*, right?
So that's like, and that's really a very worth, important point to
point out, right? That חז"ל *Chazal* are able to take a, you
know, get to the question like, you know, attitude towards slavery, attitude
towards קרבנות *Korbanot*, attitude, do we assume that everything that's in the
תורה *Torah* is a מצוה *Mitzvah*, means that the תורה *Torah* thinks
it's a לכתחילה *Lechatchila*? Or is the תורה *Torah* to some degree
accommodating realities of society? The fact that חז"ל *Chazal* could take a
phenomenon that exists, you know, you know, through so much of the
תורה *Torah*, and the תורה *Torah* never has a whiff of the
idea that there's anything problematic with it, and then they say, oh,
it's אסור *Assur* to do that. Okay.
So basically you're saying that they would equally frown upon the am...
I totally think so. Yeah. I mean, look, you could maybe argue
that when it's a case of like, you know, clearly different, like,
you know, levels of society, and clearly in poverty, whatever, sort of
like תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, you know, maybe extenuating circumstances, but anyway. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says now, so it's amazing
how in this little thing here, after 40 דף *Daf* of קידושין
kidushin *Kiddushin*, we have such this density of discussion about the nature
of קידושין *Kiddushin*, about more about the institution, right? About how much
is it a מצוה *Mitzvah* and that led to a whole conversation
about whether פרו ורבו *Pru Urvu* only takes place in the context,
fundamentally in the context of marriage? I brought in, well, okay, that
was me bringing in, it wasn't the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But anyway,
the step of two stages, קידושין *Kiddushin* and נישואין *Nisuin*, and the
importance of that, you know, but also the idea that it's fundamentally
is not about love and an emotional commitment and nevertheless חז"ל *Chazal*
want to make sure that the couple gets along and have an
attitude about men and women that they're bringing to it. So like
all of that like in this tiny little thing. And now we
switch gears again, we go, don't get too happy that we're talking
about קידושין *Kiddushin* just because it's called מסכת קידושין *Masechet Kiddushin*. We
switch gears again and we're now going to talk about the institution
of שליחות shlichus *Shlichut*, of agency, which is the basic, you know,
what the basic חידוש *Chidush* of this is that you can make
an agent. So let's take a look. Okay. So it says like
this. שליחות shlichus מנלן Menalan? *Shlichut minalan*? Where do you know that
you can create an agent to do something for you? דתניא *De-tanya*,
we learn in the ברייתא *Baraita*, ושלח *V'shalach*, so the פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* is ושלחה מביתו *V'shilcha mibeto*. Okay, he should send this woman
from his house when he divorces a woman. So we're reading it
ושלח *V'shalach*, מלמד שהוא עושה שליח shaliach, *Melamed she-oseh shaliach*, not just
to send the woman from the house, but you can make a
שליח shaliach *Shaliach*, okay? ושלחה *V'shilcha*, now that's it, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says with a מפיק ה"א *Mappik Heh*, ושלחה *V'shilcha*, right, and
he should send her, ושלחה *V'shilcha*. Okay, but we're reading it without
the מפיק ה"א *Mappik Heh*, ושלחה *V'shalcha*, which means she can make
an agent.
ושלחה ושלחה ושלחה *V'shalcha
V'shilcha V'shalcha*.
Yeah, how would you say, no? And we can debate the grammar.
Anyway, you take out the מפיק ה"א *Mappik Heh* and it becomes
a feminine verb. מלמד שהיא עושה שליח shaliach *Melamed she-ossa shaliach*. That
she can make a שליח *Shaliach*. ושלח ושלחה *V'shalach V'shalcha*, מלמד שהשליח
עושה שליח *Melamed she-shaliach oseh shaliach*. And then we somehow read it
both ways and a שליח *Shaliach* can make a שליח *Shaliach*, okay?
Although you might remember a whole discussion in גיטין *Gittin* whether מילי
מימסרן לשליח *Milei mimsran l'shaliach* and maybe do you have to have
a גט *Get*, you have to have something physical? Anyway, we're not
going to get into it right now. עד כאן מגירושין *Ad kan
mi-gerushin*. So we learned out from the word ושלחה *V'shilcha* from גירושין
girushin, *Gerushin* that there could be a שליח *Shaliach*. בקידושין מנלן Menalan?
*B'Kiddushin minalan*? How do you know a woman when it comes time
for our משנה Mishna *Mishna* to get married to make her שליח
*Shaliach*? וכי תימא דיליף מגירושין Vechay teima deyallif migirushin? *V'chi teima d'yalif
mi-gerushin*? Oh, well let's just learn it out. You know, if it
works in one case, it works in another. No. מה גירושין Girushin
שכן ישנן בעל כרחה *Mah Gerushin she-ken yeshan b'al korcha*. A גירושין
girushin, *Gerushin* can be against her will. And that really is an
important point. If it's against her will, that means two things. Number
one, it means the man has all power and control. If you
have all power and control, the fact that you're able to appoint
an agent, since it's fundamentally a one-sided transaction, hey, if you're in
charge, as who was it, Mel Brooks said, it's good to be
king, right? If you're in charge,
you know, so okay, it's more obvious. If it's a two-sided transaction
and it depends on the other person or whatever and it's not
so much clear whether it's going to end correctly or not, you
know, whether it will succeed or not succeed, it's less clear that
you can just deputize some of that, you know, power. Also from
her end, if she's just passive, there's less of a role for
her to play. So it's easier to understand how she can make
her, how she can make her שליח *Shaliach*, okay? But קידושין *Kiddushin*,
which is two-sided, right, and you have to get both sides to
have a meeting of minds and to agree and there's a judgment
call, should I marry this woman, should I marry this guy, right,
it's less clear that you can transfer that authority and you're not,
it's not all your authority. Okay. So therefore אמר
קרא amar kra, *Amar kra*, the verse says ויצאה והיתה *V'yatz'ah v'hayta*,
she shall go out and be, get married to another man. מקיש
הויה ליציאה *Maki'sh havaya l'yetziah*, connects getting married to getting divorced. מה
יציאה משווי שליח אף הויה נמי משווי שליח *Mah yetziah mashvei shaliach
af havaya nami mashvei shaliach*. By divorce you can make a
שליח *Shaliach*, by getting married also you can make a שליח *Shaliach*.
ואהא דתנן *V'ala ha detnan*, so now we know שליחות shlichus *Shlichut*
by גירושין geirushin *Gerushin* and קידושין *Kiddushin*, but now how about another
משנה Mishna, *Mishna*, another area? תרומה truma? *Terumah*. האומר לשלוחו צא תרום
לי *Ha-omer l'shlucho tze terom li*. Somebody says to his שליח *Shaliach*,
go take תרומה truma, *Terumah* for me from my grain. תורם כדעת
בעל הבית *Torem k'da'at ba'al habayit*. He takes תרומה truma. *Terumah* based
on the way he assesses how generous or stingy the owner is.
ואם אין יודע דעת בעל הבית תורם בבינוני *V'im ein yode'a da'at
ba'al habayit torem b'beinoni*. One out of
forty, two and a
half percent, an ungenerous person gives one out of sixty, 1.6 percent,
and a normal person gives two percent. So you should figure out
where your, where the person who's giving you this agency, where he
hangs, where he is on the generosity scale. And if you don't
know, go for the average. The average is two percent. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says,
I'm sorry the משנה continues in ט, Tes, פחת עשרה או הוסף
עשרה, pichas asara o hosif asara, if you go up you know
one-tenth or down one-tenth, an order of ten, meaning one-fortieth or one-sixtieth,
okay? If you go anywhere within the range, תרומתו תרומה, trumato truma,
it's still good because basically since he didn't specify more, then we
can say that he's giving you that latitude to decide or trusts
you to determine how much is appropriate and what he wants. But
what if he did more? So none of it is good or
just the one-fiftieth?
I don't know, presumably not. Anyway, we can't go off track.
מנלן? Now how do you know that שליחות shlichus works by תרומה?
truma וכי תימא דיליף מגירושין? Maybe we learn it from גירושין, geirushin
right? Once you have it in one place you'll apply it elsewhere?
No. מה לגירושין שכן יש בהן חול. Ma legirushin sheken yesh bahen
chol. גירושין geirushin is a secular matter. Maybe תרומה, truma. which relates
to something that goes to the כהנים kohanim and to God, etc.,
maybe it has different parameters? So אמר קרא, אתם גם אתם. atem
gam atem. It says כן תרימו גם אתם, ken tarimu gam atem,
right? So also you shall take תרומה. truma. Actually it's by תרומת
מעשר. trumat ma'aser. Also you, meaning the לויים Levi'im take תרומה truma.
to give to the כהנים, kohanim, not just ישראל Yisrael takes תרומה.
truma, Anyway, it doesn't matter. The point is you, even you. Who's
גם אתם? gam atem? Who's even you? Even your representative counts as
you. Okay, so that's where we learn שליחות shlichus by תרומה. truma.
לרבות את השליח. Lerabot et hashliach. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, ונכתוב רחמנא בתרומה וניתן הנך וניגמרו מינה. venichtav rachmana bitruma venesei
hanach venigmeru mina. Just write it by תרומה. truma If שליחות shlichus.
works even by the weightier area of something that's sort of more
קדוש, kadosh, it should certainly work by secular matters. No, משום דאיכא
למיפרך. mishum de'ika lemifrach. You can ask: שכן ישנה במחשבה. sheken yeshna
bemachshava. תרומה, truma you can just by thought, you can just think
that portion of the grain is תרומה. truma, Or you can just
do it by words, right? So something that's like that, so to
create an agent to do it, I mean it's not so much
that the agent has to represent my person. It's really just my
thought. In a way you could almost think of agency as a
type of ברירה. breira. You, Michael, are going to take תרומה Trumah.
for me and that's the תרומה Trumah. I would have wanted to
take. There's no need for me to do anything personally, right? So
since thought works, agency is a lot easier to explain. Because קודש
kodesh is more sensitive or vulnerable, right? It's affected even by your
thinking. That's a, okay, right. I mean it's also because it's הפלאה,
haflaa, but yes, that's a way of thinking about it. But the
point here about the שליחות shlichus is that if you need the
person to do it, if you need an act, let me say
it this way, if you need an act, you might need the
act done by the person him or herself. If it's just a
thought, well, the person already had the thought when they made a
שליח, and the שליח just sort of clarifies that thought. So, so
therefore you need to say both by something that's תרומה, Trumah which
is by thought and that's קודש, kodesh, but you also need it
by קידושין and גירושין, geirushin which is to tell you that even
by something that's not thought-based, שליחות works as well. Okay, now the
גמרא says like this: והא דתנן, veha detnan, but one minute, we
have a third category of שליחות. חבורה שאבדה פסחה. Chabura she'avda pishcha.
Oh! It's ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, and this group that got together
to bring their קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, their little lamb ran away.
Mary's little lamb ran away. ואמרו לאחד, Ve'amru le'echad, so they said
to one of their group: צא ובקש, Tze u'vakesh, go find the
lamb, ושחוט עלינו, u'shchot aleinu, and shecht it for us. Okay? והלך
ומצא ושחט. Vehalach umatza veshachat. He went, he found the lamb, and
he shechted it. He brought it to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
and shechted it. והן לקחו ושחטו, Vehen lakchu veshachatu, and then they
figured hey, he's never going to find it, so they went and
they bought another lamb and they shechted
it. אם שלו נשחט ראשון, Im shelo nishchat rishon, if he shechted
his first, הוא אוכל משלו והם אוכלים עמו. hu ochel mishelo vehem
ochlim imo.
Okay, then if he brought it first, then he, they told him
to do it, and then it works for all of them, and
then they get rid of their other lamb and they, their קרבן
פסח korban Pesach is the one he brought. Okay, it's a funny
scenario or it's an interesting one, but what's relevant for us is
they can make him, what?
Does the other lamb go to the fold?
Well, no, it would actually, but not once they sanctified it. No,
anyway, we're not going to worry about that, Michael. The point is,
is that it's a case where they made him a שליח to
shecht the קרבן פסח korban Pesach for them. Now, it's funny why
you have to quote the משנה, 'cause isn't that every single case?
You don't have ten people holding onto the knife. Okay, and to
some degree that's what the גמרא is going to say, but there
is a little bit of a difference. The difference here is is
that they, well no, forget it. Anyway, let's just stop with that.
So here you have the scenario of somebody representing them to bring
the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, okay? So you see there's an idea
of שליחות to shecht a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. מנלן? Where do
you know that from? וכי תימא ניליף מהנך? Vechay teima neillyf mehanach?
We'll learn out from these... from תרומה Trumah *Terumah*, קידושין *Kiddushin*, גירושין
*Geirushin*? No, מה להני שכן ישנן בחולין אצל קדשים Kodshim. *mah lehano
sheken yeshnan be-cholin etzel kodshim*? All of those are at a lower
level, even תרומה Trumah *Terumah* than קדשים Kodshim *Kodshim*, sacrifices at the
highest level. Maybe שליחות *shlichus* doesn't work. So גמרא *Gemara* says נפקא
ליה מרבי יהושע בן קרחה *nafka lei mi-deRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*. We
learn it from רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*, דאמר
רבי יהושע בן קרחה מנין ששלוחו של אדם כמותו *d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha minayin she-shlucho shel adam kemoso*? How do you know that
you can make a שליח *shaliach*? שנאמר ושחטו אותו כל קהל עדת
ישראל בין הערבים *Shene'emar Ve-shachatu oso kol kehal adas Yisrael bein ha'arbayim*.
All the Jewish people
should שחט *shacht*. וכי כל הקהל כולן שוחטין *Vechi kol ha-kehal kulan
shochtin*? Does everybody שחט *shacht*? והלא אינו שוחט אלא אחד *Ve-halo einu
shocheit ela echad*? Only one person presumably of each group, of each
בית אב *beis av* would שחט *shacht*. אלא מכאן ששלוחו של אדם
כמותו *Ela mikan she-shlucho shel adam kemoso*. Now the question is, why
did you have to prove it from that פסוק *pasuk* of כל
קהל עדת ישראל *kol kehal adas Yisrael*? Why didn't you just say
it says משכו וקחו לכם שה לבית אבות שה לבית *Mishchu
u-kechu lachem seh le-veis avos seh la-bayis*? Obviously only one person is
going to שחט *shacht* for each household. So here's the חידוש *chiddush*.
The חידוש *chiddush* is that if it was just that פסוק *pasuk*
I wouldn't say it's שליחות *shlichus*. I would say that's what the
תורה *Torah* says. The תורה *Torah* says you get a group together,
they become part of they're all the group for the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach *Korban Pesach*, and one person sort of שחט *shachts*, that's
the fundamental structure, right? The fundamental structure is that each group has
one person שחט *shachting*. It's not like each person has a personal
obligation to שחט *shacht*. Each group has one person שחט *shachting*. That's
not שליחות *shlichus*, that's just the way it works. Okay? But what
this is saying is no, the פסוק *pasuk* says ושחטו אותו כל
קהל עדת ישראל בין הערבים *Ve-shachatu oso kol kehal adas Yisrael bein
ha'arbayim*. This is saying everybody has to שחט *shacht*. It's not just
a group obligation, it's an individual obligation. But if it's an individual
obligation, that's not what's happening. Ah, so it must be that when
one person is doing it, he's taking he is doing your individual
obligation for you. Okay? So just to say one person שחט *shachts*
doesn't prove it's שליחות *shlichus*. But to say that everybody is supposed
to do it, each individual, and still one person only one person
of each group does it, that shows you an idea of שליחות
*shlichus*. Okay so let's just read I know we're already over, but
let's just read a little bit more to finish this thought. Okay
and it says like this: אלא מכאן *mikan*, okay, נכתב רחמנא בקדשים
ונייתי מהני *Nichtav rachmana be-kodshim u-neisi hano*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
נכתב רחמנא בקדשים ונייתי מהני וניגמור מיניה *Nichtav rachmana be-kodshim u-neisi hano
ve-nigmor mineih*? So just write by קדשים Kodshim. *Kodshim* and let's learn
it out. No, משום דאיכא למיפרך מה לקדשים שכן רוב מעשיהן על
ידי שליח *mishum d'ika le-mifrach mah le-kodshim sheken rov maseihen al yedei
shaliach*. קדשים Kodshim. *Kodshim* most things are through שליח *shaliach*. כל הנך
*Kol hano* do it. Now again the same question could be asked.
Exactly. Because who said that the כהן *kohen* I have to do
it and the כהן *kohen* is doing it for me? Maybe fundamentally
the כהן *kohen* does it. But even if you just focus on
שחיטה *shchita*, here's the point. If you look at the פסוקים *psukim*
and read the פסוקים *psukim* closely, who שחט *shachts* the קרבן *korban*?
בני אהרן הכהנים *Bnei Aharon ha-Kohanim*? No.
The פסוקים *psukim* say you bring your קרבן *korban* ושחטו אותו *ve-shachto
oso* and then it introduces בני אהרן הכהנים *Bnei Aharon ha-Kohanim*. That's
how we learn that שחיטה כשירה בזר *shchita k'sheira be-zar*. So actually
even however you think about the כהנים *kohanim* bringing קרבנות *korbanos*, who
says I'm supposed to bring, they're supposed to bring, it's not they're
my שליח *shaliach*. Okay, that's the גמרא *Gemara*'s question, are the כהנים
*kohanim* גבוה שלוחים או נן שלוחים *Gavoah shluchei or Na shluchei*? Okay,
nevertheless the תורה *Torah* describes that you're supposed to שחט *shacht*. And
the reality is is that the כהנים *kohanim* are the ones that
שחט *shacht*. Okay, so in קדשים Kodshim. *Kodshim* anyway we can assume
and I might be overreading the גמרא *Gemara*, could be the גמרא
*Gemara*'s just saying no, even in general presumably when they're working in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* doing everything, they're doing it on your
behalf. Okay, so קדשים Kodshim *Kodshim* might be an exception that we
allow representatives, whether the כהנים *kohanim* to represent or whether the בני
*bnei* one of the people of the חבורה *chaburah* to represent, we
allow representatives for קדשים Kodshim. *Kodshim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says חדא
מחברתה לא אתיא *chada michabarta lo asya*. Fine, we can't learn one
from the other. תיתי חדא מתרתי *Taisi chada mitartei*. Why do we
need all three? You can learn one from the other two. Exactly.
How would we do that? הי תיתי *Hei taisi*? Which one which
one should we learn out? לא נכתב רחמנא בקדשים ותיתי מהני *Lo
nichtav rachmana be-kodshim ve-taisi mehano* and learn out from תרומה Trumah *Terumah*
and גירושין *Geirushin*. No, מה להני שכן ישנן בחולין אצל קדשים Kodshim
*mah lehano sheken yeshnan be-cholin etzel kodshim*. That you can't say 'cause
קדשים Kodshim. *Kodshim*'s at the highest level. Okay, it's the highest holiness.
So לא נכתב רחמנא בגירושין ותיתי מהני *lo nichtav rachmana be-geirushin ve-taisi
mehano*, learn out from תרומה Trumah. *Terumah* and קדשים *Kodshim*. No, מה
להני שכן ישנן במחשבה *mah lehano sheken yeshnan be-machshava*. Again we have
the מחשבה machshavah, *machshava* point, you can make something sanctify something as
a קרבן *korban* also just through thought and speech, you don't need
an action. So maybe so you know because on the one hand
it's קודש kodesh *kodesh*, you can't learn you know it might have
a higher standard, on the other hand it's מחשבה machshavah. *machshava*, it
might have a lower standard for שליחות *shlichus*. אלא לא נכתב רחמנא
בתרומה ותיתי מהני *Ela lo nichtav rachmana be-terumah ve-taisi mehano*. Don't write
by תרומה *Terumah* and I could learn out from the other two.
'Cause if I say I can't learn out from from גירושין *Geirushin*
because it's חול chol. *chol*, I'll say אה *ah* but קדשים *Kodshim*
it applies. או *Oh* I can't learn out by קדשים *Kodshim* because
that's כל מעשיהן על ידי שליח *kol maseihen al yedei shaliach*. I
can learn out from תרומה *Terumah*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
הכי נמי *hacha nami*. You're right. So in the end and we'll
end with this and tomorrow we'll see why I needed the פסוק
*pasuk* by תרומה *Terumah* but in the end we have like this,
okay? You have קדשים *Kodshim*,
now קדשים *Kodshim* has the elements of well it's קודש kodesh *kodesh*,
okay, and it's got
מחשבה *machshava*. Okay, and it's מעשיהם על ידי שליח, ma'aseihem al yedei
shaliach. מעשיהם על ידי שליח. ma'aseihem al yedei shaliach, Okay, that's קדשים.
You've got תרומה.
I need a different color here.
Okay, it has קודש kodesh and מחשבה, but doesn't have מעשיהם על
ידי שליח, right? And then you've got
and then you've got over here, you've got גירושין which is just
basically חול.
Wait, by קדשים you mean the קרבן פסח and קודש means תרומה.
Right. So, the גמרא says, which you can't learn out from just
these two because oh and you know and it's like like less
than קדשים. I'm sorry. So the one thing here that they overlap
with is that both of them have a קדושה kedushah that is
less than קדשים. Less than קדשים. Okay, so the גמרא basically says
here's set theory, right? You
can't learn out from קדשים and תרומה because they both share this
quality, right? קודש and מחשבה. You can't learn out from תרומה from
תרומה and and גירושין because they both have a קדושה kedushah that's
less than קדשים. But what you can learn out from is גירושין
and קדשים because there's no overlap between גירושין and קדשים. So since
there's no overlap, so if it applies to those two things that
have no shared characteristics, then it must apply to everything. Okay, and
therefore תרומה is extra and we're going to find out tomorrow why
we needed the פסוק by תרומה. All right.